The cool of the evening.
In the cool of the evening, when shadows darkened the fairgrounds, Templeton
crept from the crate and looked around.
Wilbur lay asleep in the straw.
Charlotte was building a web.
Templeton's keen nose detected many fine smells in the air. The rat was hungry
and thirsty. He decided to go exploring.
Without saying anything to anybody, he started off. "Bring me back a word,"
Charlotte called after him. "I shall be writing tonight for the last time." The
rat mumbled something to himself and disappeared into the shadows. He did not
like being treated like a messenger boy.
After the heat of the day, the evening came as a welcome relief to all. The
ferris wheel was lighted now. It went round and round in the sky and seemed
twice as high as by day. There were lights on the midway and you could hear
the crackle of the gambling machines and the music of the merrygoround and the
voice of the man in the bino booth calling numbers.
The children felt refreshed after their nap. Fern met her friend Henry Fussy and
he invited her to ride with him in the ferris wheel. He even bought a ticket
for her, so it didn't cost her anything.
When Mrs. Arabel happened to look up into the starry sky and saw her little
daughter sitting with Henry Fussy and going higher and higher into the air and
saw how happy Fern looked, she just shook her head. My my, she said. Henry
Fussy, think of that.
Templeton kept out of sight. In the tall grass behind the cattle barn, he found a
folded newspaper. Inside it were leftovers from somebody's lunch, a
deileled ham sandwich, a piece of Swiss cheese, part of a hardboiled egg, and
the core of a wormy apple.
The rat crawled in and ate everything.
Then he tore a word out of the paper, rolled it up, and started back to Wilbur's pen.
Charlotte had her web almost finished when Templeton returned, carrying the
newspaper clipping. She had left a space in the middle of the web. At this hour,
no people were around the pig pin, so the rat and the spider and the pig were
by themselves.
"I hope you brought a good one," Charlotte said. "It is the last word I
shall ever write." "Here," said Templeton, unrolling the paper. What
does it say?" asked Charlotte. "You'll have to read it for me." "It says
humble," replied the rat. "Humble," said Charlotte. "Humble has two
meanings. It means not proud, and it means near the ground." "That's Wilbur
all over. He's not proud, and he's near the ground."
Well, I hope you're satisfied," sneered the rat. "I'm not going to spend all my
time fetching and carrying. I came to this fair to enjoy myself, not to deliver papers.
You've been very helpful," Charlotte said. "Run along if you want to see more
of the fair." The rat grinned. "I'm going to make a night of it," he said.
The old sheep was right. This fair is a rat's paradise. What eating and what
drinking and everywhere good hiding and good hunting.
Bye-bye, my humble Wilbur. Fair thee well, Charlotte, you old schemer. This
will be a night to remember in a rat's life. He vanished into the shadows.
Charlotte went back to her work. It was quite dark now. In the distance,
fireworks began going off, rockets scattering fiery balls in the sky. By
the time the arables and the Zuckermanmans and Lurvy returned from
the grandstand, Charlotte had finished her web. The word humble was woven
neatly in the center. Nobody noticed it in the darkness. Everyone was tired and happy.
Fern and Avery climbed into the truck and lay down. They pulled the Indian
blanket over them. Lurvy gave Wilbur a fork full of fresh straw. "Mr. Arable
patted him. "Time for us to go home," he said to the pig. "See you tomorrow."
The grown-ups climbed slowly into the truck, and Wilbur heard the engine start
and then heard the truck moving away in low speed. He would have felt lonely and
homesick had Charlotte not been with him. He never felt lonely when she was
near. In the distance, he could still hear the music of the merry-goround.
As he was dropping off to sleep, he spoke to Charlotte.
"Sk me that song again about the dung and the dark," he begged. "Not tonight,"
she said in a low voice. "I'm too tired." Her voice didn't seem to come
from her web. Where are you? asked Wilbur. I I can't see you. Are you on your web?
I'm back here, she answered. Up in this back corner.
Why aren't you on your web? asked Wilbur. You almost never leave your web.
I've left it tonight, she said. Wilbur closed his eyes. Charlotte, he said
after a while, do you really think Zuckerman will let me live and not kill
me when the cold weather comes? Do you really think so?
Of course, said Charlotte, you are a famous pig, and you are a good pig.
Tomorrow you will probably win a prize.
The whole world will hear about you.
Zuckerman will be proud and happy to own such a pig. You have nothing to fear,
Wilbur. Nothing to worry about. Maybe you'll live forever. Who knows? And now go to sleep.
For a while there was no sound. Then Wilbur's voice. What are you doing up
there, Charlotte? Oh, making something, she said. Making something as usual. Is
it something for me? asked Wilbur. No, said Charlotte. It's something for me
for a change. Please tell me what it is, begged Wilbur.
I'll tell you in the morning, she said.
When the first light comes into the sky and the sparrows stir and the cows
rattle their chains. When the rooster crows and the stars fade. When early
cars whisper along the highway. You look up here and I'll show you something. I
will show you my masterpiece.
Before she finished the sentence, Wilbur was asleep. She could tell by the sound
of his breathing that he was sleeping peacefully deep in the straw. Miles away
at the Arabble's house, the men sat around the kitchen table eating a dish
of canned peaches and talking over the events of the day.
Upstairs, Avery was already in bed and asleep. Mrs. Arable was tucking Fern
into bed. "Did you have a good time at the fair?" she asked as she kissed her
daughter. Fern nodded. I had the best time I have ever had anywhere or any
time in all of my whole life. Well, said Mrs. Herable, isn't that nice?
[Music]
Chapter 19.